萬物理論
1963年  英格蘭  劍橋
快點
Well, come on!
快點  老頭子
Come on, old man.
再不快點就晚了
I think we're going to be late!
我全速前進呢  布萊恩
Fire's on the rocket, Brian.
布萊恩找到了空隙
Brian finds an opening!
別搞砸了
Oy, don't mess up!
霍金的最後衝刺
Hawking's last minute!
謝了  布萊恩
Thanks, Brian!
太慢了  老頭子
Too slow, old man.
太慢了
Too slow.
我第一個喝到酒  你好啊
First to find a drink, yeah. Hello.
要是宇宙的奧秘跟性有關
What if the secret of the universe has something to do with sex.
你博士論文就寫這個吧  愛之物理學
Maybe do your doctorate on that? The physics of love.
-那是你的研究領域吧  -最近沒怎麼研究了
- I think that's more your field, Brian. - Not lately.
你要是再定不下來  就要被請出去了
They will boot you out, you know, if you don't decide.
我認識這裡所有的...棒極了
I know everybody here who's... brilliant.
居然是科學家們
Oh, dear, scientists!
別擔心  不會待太久的
Don't worry, we don't have to stay long...
簡直無聊到死
looks mortifyingly dull.
-沒勁  -那是誰
- Bores. - Who's that?
哪個  他嗎
Who's who? Oh, him?
他可怪了  不過他也去了抗議核遊行[1960年代]
He's strange. However, he goes to ban the bomb marches.
Y  縮寫是GY
Y... G.Y.
大衛在那  大衛
Oh, there's David... David?
戴安娜
Diana?
-你好  -你好
- Hello. - Hello.
-理學嗎  -文學
- Science? - Arts.
-英語  -法語及西班牙語
- English. - French and Spanish.
那你呢  你學什麼的
What about you? What are you?
-宇宙學家  我是個宇宙學家  -那是什麼
- Cosmologist, I'm a cosmologist. - What's that?
就是特別聰明的  不信上帝的人
It's a kind of religion for
-信的宗教  -聰明的不信上帝的
- intelligent atheists. - Intelligent atheists?
你不信教吧
You're not religious, are you?
國教
C. Of E.
-就是英國國教[聖公會]  -是啊
- Church of England. - England, yes.
總得有個信教的
I suppose someone has to be.
那宇宙學家信奉什麼呢
So, what do cosmologists worship then?
信奉什麼
What do we worship?
用一個統一的方程
One single unifying equation
來解釋宇宙萬物
that explains everything in the universe.
-是嗎  -是
- Really. - Yes.
是什麼方程
What's the equation?
問題就在這
That is the question.
這個問題非常好  我還沒想出來
And a very good question. I'm not quite sure yet.
但我想研究這個
But I intend to find out.
那你為什麼去牛津啊
Then why do you even stay at Oxford?
因為我的期末考試
Because my finals exams are such a
考得一塌糊塗  他們叫我參加個口試
shambles that the examiners they settled me in for a "Viva",
-他們如果我拿到二等  -口試是什麼
- And they told me that if I go up a second... - What's a "Viva"?
有點恐怖  跟人面對面坐下來什麼的
A sort of, mildly terrifying face-to-face thingy.
-面試嗎  -審訊吧
- As an interview? - An interrogation.
我告訴他們  如果給我二等學位[參考片尾注釋]
And I told them that if they gave me a 2nd class degree
我就得留在牛津做研究
then I'd stay with them and do my research at Oxford,
如果給我一等學位  我就能去劍橋了
but if they gave me the 1st, I needed to get into Cambridge, then
他們就能永遠甩掉我了
they would never have to see me again.
-所以他們給了你一等  -沒錯
- They gave you the 1st. - They gave me the 1st.
-是啊  -派對已經正式結束了
- Of course. - This party is officially deceased.
來吧  我找輛車送你回家
Come on, I've fixed you up a ride home.
走啊  簡  簡
Come on, Jane... Jane?
-跟你聊天很開心  -我也是
- Well, it was lovely to talk to you. - Yes.
還有  希望你能找到那個方程
And... I hope you find your equation.
是啊
Yes... oh...
-再見  -再見
- Bye. - G'bye.
斯蒂芬
Stephen?
很好
Good.
來看看這個
Well, then, here we are,
給你們的小測試
a little challenge for you all,
在你們的學術研究路上...
as you embark upon your separate doctoral journeys...
不管你們打算研究什麼  霍金先生
whatever they may be, Mr. Hawking.
傳下去
Pass them down.
來看看你們是男人還是男孩
Something to separate the men from the boys,
是糧食還是糟糠
the wheat from the chaff,
介子還是π介子  真誇克[基本粒子之一]還是假行家
the mesons from the pi-mesons, the quarks from the quacks.
十個問題  一個比一個難
Ten questions, each more impregnable than the last.
祝你們好運吧  週五三點再見
Good luck, you'll need it. Shall we say Friday at 3 o'clock?
我要做到癱瘓了
This is going to hospitalize me.
好了  劃  劃  劃  劃
All right! Row! Row! Row! Row!
使勁劃  布萊恩  加油啊
Row it out, Brian! Come on, Brian!
劃  布萊恩  加油
Row, Brian! Come on! Row, Brian.
向前進  布萊恩
Straight on, Brian!
再來兩杯這個
Can I get two more of those, please?
-換點零錢打個電話  -好的
- And some change for phone, Sir. - Yeah.
-不拿走嗎  -簡
- Take her out, man. - Jane.
猜我那天碰到誰了  卡洛琳
You'll never guess who I saw the other day... Caroline.
她好像有男朋友了  不過她愛約誰約誰
I think she was having a date, she can have him, quite frankly.
這概率有多大
What's the probability?
小的不得了
Reasonably low.
這個  這是斯蒂芬
Uh... this is... this is Stephen.
-你玩槌球嗎  -槌球
- Do you play croquet? - Croquet?
-有陣子沒玩了  -周日早上
- Not recently. - Sunday morning.
我周日早上有事
I'm actually busy on Sunday mornings.
是啊  跟上帝[做禮拜]
Oh... Him.
好吧
Okay.
快起床  你做出了幾個
Oh, come on, get up! How many did you get?
-早上好  布萊恩  -下午好  斯蒂芬
- Morning, Brian. - Good afternoon, Stephen.
那幾個問題你做出幾個
How many of the possible questions did you do?
布萊恩  你在說什麼啊
Brian, I have no idea what you're talking about.
夏瑪的問題  你做出幾個  斯蒂芬
How many of Sciama's questions did you get, Stephen?
-沒做  -一個沒做嗎
- None. - You didn't get any?
我一會再做
I was going to do them later.
你看都沒看
You haven't even looked at them.
沒看
No.
斯蒂芬  你知道自己
Stephen, are you aware that
是自願攻讀物理學博士學位的吧
you've voluntarily embarked on a PhD in physics?
還是在英國最頂尖的大學裡
At the most prestigious college in England?
知道
Yes.
還以為入學典禮時候你睡著了呢
Oh! Thought maybe you'd slept through the induction or something.
布萊恩
Brian?
-怎麼了  -放段瓦格納吧
- What? - Can you whip on some Wagner?
一邊去
Sod off!
-請進  斯蒂芬  -抱歉
- Come in, Stephen. - Sorry.
邁克  你這亂成一坨
Michael, that's so illegible
我也不知道你錯了多少  估計是不少
I can't quite decipher how wrong it is, I suspect enormously,
布萊恩  看不懂你寫的什麼
and Brian... that's just baffling.
-您受累做了沒  -抱歉
- Have you even bothered to? - Oh, sorry.
列車時刻表
Train time tables.
這怎麼行  這時刻表都過期了
It's certainly unacceptable, these expired a month ago.
在背面  我出了點事
It's on the back, I had a little accident.
只能做出九個
I could only do nine.
好吧  謝天謝地  那個
Well... oh... thank God... however...
九個
Nine?
請進
Come in.
斯蒂芬  坐吧
Oh, Stephen, take a seat.
我想談談你的課題
I wanted to talk to you about your subject.
我們都等著你決定研究方向呢
We're all rather concerned as to what it's going to be.
我定不下來
I can't decide.
有什麼想法嗎
Do you have any ideas?
沒有
No.
湯普森在這發現了電子[1897年]
This is where J.J. Thomson discovered the electron,
盧瑟福在這分裂了原子核[1909年]
and where Rutherford split the atom.
在劍橋搞研究的好處就是  你永遠都不知道
You know, one of the great rewards of this job is one never knows
誰  在哪裡
from where the next great
能搞出個重大發現來
leap forward is going to come, or from whom.
下週五  我要帶幾個優秀研究生去倫敦
Next Friday, I'm taking a few graduates of merit to London,
參加數學家羅傑•彭羅斯的講座
to attend a talk by the mathematician Roger Penrose.
你也來吧  如果有興趣的話
You come along... if you're interested.
走的時候記得關門
Oh, and close the door as you leave.
聽說你從沒去過教堂
So, I gather you've never been to church?
-很久以前去過  -想信教嗎
- Once upon a time. - Tempted to convert?
我不太信這種統領萬物的神
I have a slight problem with the whole Celestial Dictator premise.
你午飯有安排嗎  我媽烤的肉特別好吃
Now, what are you doing for lunch? Ma makes a cracking roast.
簡  你是學什麼的
So, Jane, what are you studying?
-文學  -要球甘藍嗎
- Arts. - Sprouts?
謝謝
Thank you.
法語和西班牙語  畢業希望繼續讀博
French and Spanish, and hoping to do a PhD eventually.
哪個方向呢
Oh, one arm.
中世紀伊波利亞半島詩歌
Medieval poetry of the Iberian Peninsula.
中世紀詩歌...你喜歡哪位畫家
Medieval poets... What painters do you like?
-我喜歡特納  -特納嗎
- Well, I like Turner. - Turner, really?
我一直覺得他的畫
You know, I always feel that his
像是被暴雨泡了好幾天
paintings look as if they've been left out in the rain.
還有  威廉•佈雷克
And... William Blake.
-簡  來嘗嘗我的接骨木酒  -謝謝
- Jane, have some of my elderflower wine. - Yes, yes, thank you.
別試  別試  簡
Don't touch it, don't touch it, Jane.
謝謝  他媽呢
Thank you. Mother.
斯蒂芬不喜歡我自己釀的酒  菲麗西汀呢
Stephen doesn't like my homemade wine...Philistine.
給你塞幾瓶帶回學校
I'm going to send you back with a couple of bottles.
斯蒂芬  你和這位善良的女士去了教堂
So, Stephen, you have come to church with a good woman.
覺得自己聖潔嗎
Are you feeling holier than thou?
非常聖潔  謝謝
Positively saintly... thank you.
你還沒說自己為什麼不信上帝
You haven't said why you don't believe in God.
物理學家的研究
A physicist can't allow his calculations
不能受超自然的創世主影響
to be muddled by a belief in a supernatural creator.
你說得像是在指責物理學家啊
Sounds less of an argument against God than against physicists.
雞胸還是雞腿
Light or dark?
-簡  雞胸還是雞腿  -雞胸  謝謝
- Jane, light meat or dark? - Light, please.
我要請簡做我五月舞會[劍橋傳統]的舞伴
I'm inviting Jane to be my partner for the May ball.
真的嗎  真棒
Really! Very impressive!
你要跳舞了  斯蒂芬
You'll have to dance, won't you, Stephen?
給女僕讓個路  好了
Make way for my mother's maid, here we go.
你好
Hello.
-抱歉  -你沒事吧
- Sorry. - Are you okay?
-跳舞吧  -不跳
- Should we dance? - No.
不跳了
No.
我不跳  雖然我很喜歡看別人跳
I don't. It's a phenomenon I'm very happy to observe,
但我自己是不會跳的
but I can't possibly imagine participating.
我也這麼想的  誰願意跳舞啊
I absolutely agree. I mean, who would want to dance?
說真的  我不跳舞
No, I'm serious, I don't dance.
那就不跳了
No dancing then.
你看男生的襯衫前胸
Do you see how the men's shirt-fronts
還有領結  比女生的禮服還閃亮
and their bow ties how they glow more than the womens' dresses?
-是啊  -知道為什麼嗎
- Yes. - Do you know why?
-為什麼  -汰漬
- Why? - Tide.
洗衣粉
Washing powder.
洗衣粉裡的螢光物質在紫外線照射下發光
The fluorescence in the washing powder is caught by the UV light.
你怎麼知道的
Why do you know that?
恒星誕生和毀滅時  會輻射出紫外線
When stars are born and when they die, they emit UV radiation.
如果只能看到夜空裡的紫外線
So, if we could see the night sky in ultraviolet light,
現在的星星就都不見了
then almost all the stars would disappear
只剩下恒星壯麗的誕生和毀滅
and all that we would see are these spectacular births and deaths.
-我覺得應該...  -就像這個
- And I reckon it would look a little... - Like that.
-為什麼  -什麼為什麼
- So, why? - Why what?
為什麼要研究中世紀西班牙詩歌
Why Spanish medieval poetry?
應該是我喜歡穿越時空吧...
I suppose I like to time travel...
...像你一樣
...like you.
有哪段時空是你特別想去的嗎
Are there any particular time periods that you'd like to visit?
-二十年代吧  -咆哮的二十年代嗎[1920  北美]
- The imagine it's the Twenties. - The Roaring Twenties?
耶茨  《The Song of the Happy Shepherd》
"不要在天文學家那找尋知識
"Seek, then, No learning from starry men,
"他們只是用望遠鏡
"Who follow with the optic glass
"追隨恒星紛飛的路徑"
"The whirling ways of stars that pass."
真棒
Bravo!
"創世之初  只有天地
"In the beginning was the heaven and the earth,
大地混沌  沒有定型"
and the earth was without form,"
"黑暗籠罩著深淵"
"And darkness was upon the face of the deep."
和我共舞一曲吧
Would you dance with me?
三號月臺  前往倫敦國王十字車站的列車
The train now departing from track number three is
將於九點十五發車
the nine-fifteen service to London King's Cross.
快點  斯蒂芬  快點
Come on, Stephen. Get a move on.
怎麼了你  快上來
What's wrong with you, man? Come up top.
一顆恒星  體積是太陽的三倍多
A star, more than three times the size of our sun...
就要走到盡頭  怎麼結束呢  坍落
ought to end its life, how? With a collapse.
整顆恒星的引力
The gravitational forces of the entire mass overcoming
克服了原子之間的斥力
the electromagnetic forces of individual atoms,
向內坍落
and so collapsing inwards.
如果品質足夠大  還會繼續坍落
If the star is massive enough, it will continue this collapse,
形成一個黑洞  翹曲了時空
creating a black hole, where the warping of space-time
什麼都逃不出去  包括光
is so great that nothing can escape... not even light.
變得越來越小  越小
It gets... smaller... smaller.
恒星的密度越來越大
The star, in fact, gets denser
原子  甚至原子內的粒子都被壓縮了
as atoms, even subatomic particles get literally crushed into smaller and smaller space.
那最終  我們得到了什麼
And at its end point what are we left with?
時空奇點
A space time singularity.
時空在這裡停止
Space and time come to a stop.
我在想  如果把彭羅斯的理論
I wonder what would happen if you applied
從黑洞推廣到整個宇宙呢
Penrose's theory about black holes to the entire universe?
如果愛因斯坦是對的
If Einstein is right,
或者說廣義相對論是對的  那宇宙是在膨脹的
or if general relativity is correct, then the universe is expanding, yes?
對吧
Yes?
-對  -好了
- Yes. - Okay, so...
如果時光倒流  宇宙就是在縮小
If you reverse time, then the universe is getting smaller.
-沒錯  -那麼
- All right. - So...
如果一路倒退回去
What if I reverse the process all the way
回到時間的起點呢
back to see what happened at the beginning of Time itself?
-時間的起點  -對
- The beginning of Time itself? - Yes.
宇宙越來越小
The universe, getting smaller and smaller,
密度越來越大  溫度越來越高
getting denser and denser, hotter and hotter as...
隨著時間的倒流
As you wind back the clock.
-沒錯  時光倒流  -時光倒流
- Exactly, you wind back the clock. - Wind back the clock.
你是想讓時光倒流嗎[逆時針]
Is that what you're doing? You're winding back the clock.
沒錯
Exactly what I'm doing.
繼續轉  還有好久呢  繼續轉
Well, keep winding! You've got quite a way to go! Keep winding.
我怕摔倒
I don't want to fall down.
你得回到時間的起點
Well, you've got to go back to the beginning of time.
可有你轉的  接著轉  別停
You've got a long way to go, so, keep winding, keep winding!
直到...
Until you get...
奇點
A singularity.
時空奇點
A space-time singularity,
宇宙源自黑洞的爆炸
so the universe born from a black hole exploding.
-繼續  -繼續什麼
- Keep going. - What do you mean, "Keep going", what...
宇宙起源之前嗎
before the universe began?
不是  繼續  用數學來解決
No, no, no, no! Keep going, develop the mathematics!
用力頂  用力頂
Push it as hard as you can! Push it, push it!
-用力  -我用力了
- As hard as you can. - I am pushing as hard as I can.
怎麼...  一  二  一  二
What... I count 1... 1, 2... 1, 2...
好了
All right, all right.
無名指  第四個夾子
Fourth finger, fourth peg.
是運動神經元病
It's called motor neuron disease.
神經元逐步失調
It's a progressive neurological disorder
導致控制肌肉運動的腦細胞受損
that destroys the cells in the brain that control essential muscle activity,
比如
such as...
講話  行走  呼吸  吞咽
Speaking, walking, breathing, swallowing
控制肌肉運動的電信號收到了干擾
The signals that muscles must receive in order to move are disrupted.
結果就是肌肉逐步萎縮
The result is... gradual muscle decay, wasting away.
最終  喪失
Eventually, the ability to
運動能力  徹底地
control voluntary movement is... lost... entirely.
平均壽命是發病後兩年
I'm afraid average life expectancy is two years.
我也無能為力
There's nothing I can do for you.
大腦呢
What about the brain?
大腦不受影響  你的思想依然在
The brain isn't affected, you're thoughts won't change.
就是
It's... just that...
到最後  沒人能知道你在想什麼了
Well, eventually, no one will know what they are.
非常抱歉
I'm ever so sorry.
歡迎收看本周的自然世界
Well, welcome to this week's episode of "The Natural World",
這次  我們將一起探索劍橋一位傑出物理學家
where this week we explore the bizarre hibernation patterns
他的冬眠規律
of the rare Cambridge Physicist,
就是盛裝的這位
seen here in his remarkable plumage..."
怎麼樣  他們怎麼說的  你的手腕怎麼樣
So, how was it? What did they say, how's your wrist?
我病了  布萊恩
I have a disease, Bri.
是花柳病嗎  斯蒂芬
Is it venereal... Stephen?
是運動神經元病
I have motor neuron disease.
不好意思
Sorry, I don't...
盧•葛雷克病  他是個棒球運動員
It's Lou Gehrig's disease, he's a baseball player.
不好意思  神經運動  棒球什麼的病
Sorry, I'm lagging behind in my pioneering research into
我還沒深入研究過
skilled motor, baseball related diseases.
-我還剩兩年  -什麼
- I have two years to live. - Sorry?
大聲說出來就不那麼怪了是吧
It does sound odd when you say it out loud, doesn't it?
什麼意思  你幹什麼
Whatchya mean? What are you doing?
他們  他們
What did... what did... what...
他們怎麼說的  我剛沒仔細...
what did they say? Sorry, I... I don't really...
走吧  布萊恩
Will you go, Brian?
斯蒂芬  是我太蠢了
Stephen, I was just being a berk...
我沒...我肯定...
I didn't... I'm so... I'll be...
走吧
You go.
斯蒂芬  找你的電話  是個姑娘
Stephen, phone for you. It's a girl.
-回頭見  好的
- I'll see you soon. - Yes.
她在等著呢
She's waiting.
斯蒂芬
Stephen?
-簡  -布萊恩
- Jane! - Brian.
真抱歉  我
I'm sorry... I'm...
你坐下吧
Why don't you sit down.
真抱歉  是斯蒂芬的事
I'm so sorry. It's about Stephen.
他之前住院...
You know he was in hospital...
有教育意義嗎
Something educational?
非常有
Very.
約翰跟瑪莎有外遇
John is having an affair with Martha,
可瑪莎愛著阿蘭
but Martha is in love with Alan,
不過阿蘭應該是同性戀
and I think that Alan is probably homosexual,
看他的毛衣  我呢  我在盡力
by the look of his jumper, so, well, I'm just trying
計算他們幸福的可能性
to work out the mathematical probability of happiness.
要算出來了嗎
Are you close?
應該是零點幾  不過還差著遠呢
It's some integer of zero, but, no, I'm not quite there yet.
-斯蒂芬  -他剛走
- Stephen. - You just missed him.
之前還在這
He was here earlier.
別這樣
Don't do this.
走吧
Go!
好吧
Okay.
跟我玩個遊戲
Play a game with me.
快走
Go!
你要是不站起來跟我打一場
If you don't get up and play a game with me...
我就不回來了
I won't come back here again...
永遠不來了
...ever.
來吧
Come on!
你走吧
You can leave me now.
你不想談談嗎
Are you going to talk about this or not?
-快走不好嗎  -你想要我走嗎
- Will you please just go? - Is that what you want?
是  我想要你走  走吧
Yes, it is what I want, so, please,
你要是還在乎我  就走吧
if you care about me all, then, please, just go!
-不行  -我只剩兩年了
- I can't. - I have two years to live.
-我還要工作  -我愛你
- I need to work. - I love you.
你這  你得出了錯誤結論
You've... you've leapt to... that's a false conclusion...
我要和你在一起  有多就是多久
I want us to be together, for as long as we've got,
時間不長的話
and if that's not very long then, well,
也沒事  兩年也夠
that's just how it is... it'll have to do.
你不知道會怎麼樣  我的一切都受影響
You don't know what's coming. It'll affect everything.
你眼鏡總是這麼髒
Your glasses are always dirty.
給你
There.
好多了吧
That's better, isn't it?
嗯
Yes.
是啊
Yes, it is.
...在盒子邊緣
...the solutions to the Schrodinger
薛定諤方程是無解的  所以...
equation must vanish at the boundary of the box, so we have...
時間
Time!
你的課題是時間嗎
Time, that's your subject?
有具體方向嗎
Any aspect in particular?
就是時間
Time.
請進  請進
Come in, come in.
你應該不知道自己面對的是什麼  簡
I don't think you realize what lies ahead, Jane.
他的壽命非常短
His life is going to be very short.
要小心  你是在和科學作對
So, be careful, the weight of science is against you.
而且你沒有抗爭的機會
And this will not be a fight, Jane.
我們都會被打敗
This is going to be a very heavy defeat...
...所有人
...for all of us.
我知道你們都怎麼想
I know what you all think... that...
覺得我不是很堅強
That I don't look a terribly strong person.
可我愛他
But I love him.
他也愛我
And he loves me.
我們要一起抗爭...
We're going to fight this illness together...
...大家一起
...all of us.
祝你好運
Good luck.
-早上好  斯蒂芬  -早上好  雷夫
- Good morning, Stephen. - Good morning, Rev.
我知道  我知道
I know, I know...
-...方程要更優雅一點  -是啊
- ...got to be a little more elegant. - Yes, that's what...
我懂...
I understand...
進來吧  斯蒂芬
Come in, Stephen.
我知道  一開始都擔心這個
I know it's something we're all worried about initially.
你保留了些意見...
You had some reservations about it...
等著瞧吧
Well, well, we'll see.
-歡迎  斯蒂芬  -早上好
- Welcome, Stephen. - Morning.
-請坐吧  -不用  謝謝
- Would you like to take a seat? - No, I'm fine, thank you.
確定嗎
You're sure?
好吧  總體來說
So, so you... in summary.
第一章  漏洞百出
As we know, chapter one, full of holes.
缺乏數理支持
Lacks mathematical support.
-基普•索恩教授  -第二章  原創的
- Professor Thorne. - Chapter Two, now, really original.
用了不少羅傑的觀點
Uses a lot of Roger's ideas.
至少你還支持我的觀點
Well, at least you run with them.
第三章  留了太多疑問
Chapter three, too many unanswered questions.
沒錯
I agree.
當然了  還有第四章
And then, of course, we have chapter four,
時間起點的黑洞
this black hole at the beginning of time.
-時空奇點  -沒錯
- Space-time singularity? - Indeed.
太棒了
It's brilliant!
Brilliant.
棒極了
Superb!
那麼只剩下一句話了  做得不錯
And therefore, all that remains to be said is: Well done!
或者準確點說
Or perhaps, I should say, to be more precise:
-做的不錯  博士  -漂亮  斯蒂芬
- Well done, Doctor! - Bravo, Stephen.
這理論真不錯
An extraordinary theory.
謝謝
Thank you.
-然後呢  -證明它
- So what next? - Prove it.
用一個方程證明  時間是有起點的
To prove, with a single equation, that time had a beginning.
是不是很棒  教授
Wouldn't that be nice, Professor?
一個簡單  優美的方程
With one simple elegant equation
來解釋萬物
to explain everything?
是啊  肯定很棒
Yes, it would. It would indeed.
受人尊敬的  能力超群的
The esteemed, and formidable...
-博士  -誰[神秘博士]
- Doctor. - Who?
斯蒂芬•霍金博士
Doctor Stephen Hawking.
敬斯蒂芬•霍金
To Stephen Hawking.
謝謝  簡
Thank you, Jane.
真神奇  他是第一個擔心自己努力不夠
It is astonishing that he's the first person
還能拿到博士學位的人
to receive his doctorate fearing what little work he's be doing.
努力是霍金最討厭的詞
"Work" Was the worst four-letter word for Stephen.
甚至在牛津
Even at Oxford,
他平均每天只學習一個小時  一個小時
especially, he averaged an hour, an HOUR a day he averaged.
-就這樣  斯蒂芬就是...  -真是神奇  我一開始...
- And that it is. It's Stephen... - It's astonishing that...
過去六個月
And how many of your
我幫你們回了多少信
letters have I covered in the last six months?
你們外出搞研究時候
When you've been doing research trips...
-多少  -四封
- How many? - Four.
-沒事吧  -沒事  我沒事
- Everything all right? - I'm good... I'm fine.
你好啊  羅賓
Hi, Robin.
我沒事
It's ok. I'm all right.
真...是...
This...is...
告訴布萊恩
Tell Brian.
好啊
Of course.
方便吃早飯了
Well, it's convenient for breakfast!
謝謝
Thank you.
你剛說什麼了
Sorry, did you say something?
我說...
I said...
什麼
Yes?
謝謝
Thank you.
看看你
Look at you!
去吧  簡
Go, Jane.
馬上回來
I'll be one second.
露絲  寶貝
Luce, Baby.
簡
Jane.
斯蒂芬
Stephen.
親愛的
Dear?
我有了個想法
I've got an idea.
我說我有了個想法
I said I've had an idea.
-你好  -你好  鄧尼斯
- Hello. - Hi, Dennis.
-你好  鄧尼斯  -你好
- Hello, Dennis. - Hi.
好了  我愛你
Okay, I love you.
他沒事的  他沒事的
He'll be fine, he'll be fine.
-抱歉  沒關係
- Sorry. - No problem.
...我們可以推斷
...allowing us to predict that
有些粒子  是可以逃離黑洞的
some particles can in fact escape a black hole.
黑洞  並不是那麼黑的
The black holes are not, in fact, black at all,
它散發著熱輻射
but glow with heat radiation.
...也就是說
...the steady emission of
黑洞在穩定地輻射熱能  損失品質
heat energy causes the black holes to lose mass,
最終以爆炸的方式消失
and eventually they disappear in a spectacular explosion.
非常  非常簡單  物體散發熱量
It's very, very simple, when a hot body loses heat...
熱力學第二定理
Second law of thermodynamics.
-沒錯  熱力學  -就在...
- He's right, it's thermodynamics. - In... in...
想像一下  如果的確
If we can imagine that the black hole is, indeed,
有粒子不斷逃離黑洞
losing particles, then,
那假以時日  黑洞的體積就會減小  會蒸發
over time it will diminish in size, it will evaporate.
-然後  -消失
- It will... - Disappear.
所以
So...
首先  恒星消失  坍落成黑洞
First a star vanishes into a black hole,
然後  黑洞也要...
but then the black hole itself must...
消失  虛無
Gone! Nothing!
-從虛無到虛無  -你欠我杯啤酒
- From nothing to nothing. - You owe me another beer.
我得告訴你
I have to show you that our
我們的朋友證明了時間是有起點的
friend has proven that time, indeed has a beginning.
不僅是這個  還有宇宙如何出現  如何消亡
Not only that, how the universe was born, and how it will end.
-砰  -哢嚓
- Bang! - Crunch!
多美  多生動
It's beautiful! It's racy!
真荒唐  胡言亂語
Complete nonsense. It's preposterous.
是因為我說的東西嗎  教授
Was it something I said, Professor?
抱歉
Excuse me.
我叫
My name...
我是卡拉提諾夫教授
My name is Professor Khalatnikov.
來自蘇維埃理工學院
from Soviet Academy of Sciences.
我的研究領域  是熱宇宙的演化
As you know, my field is evolution of the hot universe,
宇宙微波背景輻射的性質
the properties of the microwave background radiation,
還有黑洞理論
and theory of the black holes.
說實話...
To be honest...
我今天來...
I came here today...
...就是想聽胡言亂語的
...expecting to hear a lot of nonsense.
然後失望地回家
I go home disappointed.
這位小夥子做到了
The little one here... has done it.
他做到了
He has done it!
見到你真榮幸
It has been a pleasure to meet you,
-教授  -彼此彼此
- Professor. - Likewise, likewise.
-還算順利嘛  -是挺順利的
- That went pretty well. - It's probably for awhile.
霍金輻射  這位小夥子做到了
Hawking radiation! The little one has done it!
這位小夥子做到了
The little one has done it!
-快點  天才  -真好笑
- Come on, Genius! - Oh, very funny!
就推你到這了  老頭子
You've had enough of that, Old Man.
用力  小子  1  2  3
Come on, codger. 1, 2, 3...
天哪  簡是怎麼做到的
God! How does Jane manage?
斯蒂芬  你那個運動口腔什麼的病  會不會影響...
Stephen, your Motor "Mouth" Disease, does it effect...
什麼
What?
一切
Everything?
另一套系統  自動的
Different system... automatic.
真的嗎
You serious?
那還算不錯嘛
Well, that's a bit wonderful, isn't it?
對男人的理解又進了一步
Well, it certainly explains a lot about men.
快點
Hurry up! Come on!
霍金輻射
-裡面有什麼  -驚喜
- What's in there? - It's a surprise!
別睜開
Keep them closed.
爸爸  快看
Look, Daddy, look!
這是電動輪椅
That is an electric wheelchair.
不喜歡的話可以退回去
If you don't like it, we can take it back.
我不明白...
I don't understand...
你花了好多年假設黑洞存在
you've spent years assuming black holes exist, and
你相信天鵝座X-1星很可能
you believe Cygnus X-1 could well turn out to be
是我們能觀測到的第一個黑洞
the first black hole that we can actually observe,
卻還跟基普•索恩賭它不是
and yet you bet Kip Thorne it's not a black hole?
-是的  -賭什麼
- Yes. - What did you bet him?
賭一年的雜誌
A one year's subscription to a magazine.
-什麼雜誌  《自然》嗎  -不是  《閣樓》
- Which magazine? Nature? - No! Penthouse!
-《閣樓》嗎  -沒錯
- Penthouse? - Yes.
抓到你了
Gonna get you!
爸爸  快點  得快點
Daddy! Come up! You need to hurry!
媽媽  媽媽  快來看
Mummy! Muumy! Come and look!
抓到你了
I'm gonna get you!
一整天  一整天  一整天  一整天
All that day! All that day! All that day! All that day!
-你好  -你好
- Hello! - Hello!
-你好  -來了啊
- Hello! - There you are!
你好  布希
Hello, Bush.
這該死的臺階  弗蘭克
The bloody steps, Frank.
-簡  斯蒂芬  -你好
- Jane, Stephen! - Hello.
終於來了
Here we are!
好了
Yes, here we go.
等上去了就方便多了  你好啊  斯蒂芬
And once we're up at the top, it's very snug... hello, Stephen.
好了
Here we go.
-來給你轉個身  -要我推一下嗎
- We'll turn you around, Stephen. - You want me to push?
不用  我沒事  你去拿行李吧
No, no, I'll be fine, you get the luggage.
好了  我來
Here we go, off, we got it.
好了  多簡單
There we are, you see. Quite easy.
上了一級
One, there we go.
下雨了  冷得讓人發抖
Um... the... rain coming down, shivering, cold, no, uh...
下了  下了
The... falling... falling... um...
-非常冷  -是什麼
- Very cold. - What is it?
我...我不太...
I can... I'm having a...
出來了嗎
Is it out?
-要點水嗎  -不用  沒事
- Some... some water? - No, don't worry.
好了  沒事了
You're okay. That's it.
沒事了  沒事了
There we go. It's okay. It's okay.
得去看醫生
He needs to see a specialist.
老是這樣
It keeps happening over and over again.
-不看醫生  不看醫生  -好  不看
- No doctors. No doctors! - All right, no doctors.
來點水
A little water.
斯蒂芬
Stephen?
我需要幫手
I need help.
為了羅伯特  他的童年都被我拖累了
If only for Robert, it... he's missing out on his childhood.
我想努力把這個家經營下去
I keep looking for a way to make this work,
可我一個人做不到
but I can't find it on my own.
沒問題啊  我們是個正常的家庭
Everything is fine, we're just a normal family.
哪裡正常了
We're not a normal family.
We're not a normal family!
羅伯特  你媽媽對我非常生氣
Robert, your mother is very angry with me.
謝謝啊
Thanks.
簡
Jane?
簡  停下
Jane! Stop!
坐下
Sit!
好了...
Now...
我給你提個建議
I'd like to make a suggestion.
聽著有點奇怪  可也幫過大忙
It might sound unusual, but I have seen it work wonders.
我覺得你應該加入唱詩班
I think that you should consider joining the church choir.
媽媽
Mum...
我好久都沒聽過
I think that's possibly
這麼貼心的話了
the most English thing anyone has ever said.
也許吧
Maybe so.
-我以前喜歡唱歌  -唱得挺好的
- I used to love singing. - You're very good at it.
-可我也不確定  -去吧
- I don't know about that. - Just go.
每週一小時
It's one hour a week.
真棒  大夥下周見
Really lovely, everyone. Okay, see you next week.
-你好  -你好
- Hello. - Hello.
-是要加入唱詩班嗎  -我是來...
- Have you come to sing? - Um... I just came to...
-高音嗎  -中音
- Soprano? - Mezzo.
太棒了  正需要中音
Ah! Lovely! Just what we need.
-你早去哪了  -問得好
- Where have you been hiding? - A good question.
反正來得早不如來得巧
Well, you're here now and just in time.
俗話說的
As they say.
-反正我還要回來的  -好
- Ya know, I have to come back anyway. - Great.
-都給你了嗎  -是的  謝謝
- Do you have everything? - Yes, thank you, yes.
謝謝你  你肯定是...團裡的中流砥柱
Thank you for coming, you will be a... A valuable asset.
謝謝
Thank you.
我  我該走了
Well, I should... I should be going.
要是你兒子想學鋼琴...
And... uh... if your son wants those piano lessons, just...
是啊  沒問題
Yes, yes, absolutely, I... um...
-肯定找你  -真棒
- I will do. - Great.
我丈夫也喜歡音樂
My... my husband... adores music, too.
他彈什麼樂器嗎
Oh! Well! Does he play?
我也可以教他的
I could... I could teach him as well.
說來話長  不過...
That's a long story. But, um...
好吧
Ah, okay.
-謝謝你  喬納森  -不客氣  簡  再見
- Well, thank you, Jonathan - My pleasure, Jane, see you again.
-再見  -再見
- Bye bye. - Bye bye.
要酒嗎
Wine?
好啊  謝謝
Why not, thank you.
-斯蒂芬  -要
- Stephen? - Yes.
斯蒂芬  簡跟我說  你有個優美的理論
Stephen, Jane was telling me you have a beautiful theorem...
證明宇宙是有開端的
...that... that proves the universe had a beginning?
我的博士論文
That was my PhD thesis.
我的新課題證明那是錯的
My new project disproves it.
是錯的
Disproves it?
Yes.
那你不再相信創世理論了
So, then, you no longer believe in the Creation?
在物理學裡  人信仰什麼是...
What one believes is irrelevant...
...是不重要的
...irrelevant in physics.
好吧
I see.
斯蒂芬來了個大轉彎
Stephen's done a U-turn.
新的理論是宇宙沒有邊界
The big new idea is that the universe has no boundaries at all.
沒有邊界  沒有開端...
No boundaries, no beginning...
...也沒有上帝
...and no God. Oh!
明白了  我還以為
Oh, I see... I... I thought that...
你證明宇宙有開端
you'd proved the universe
進一步證明有創世主
had a beginning and thus a need for a Creator.
-我的錯  -是我的
- My mistake. - No... mine.
斯蒂芬想找到一個理論
Stephen is looking for a single theory
來解釋宇宙中的一切
that explains all the forces in the universe.
這樣上帝就必須死
Therefore, God must die.
為什麼上帝必須死  我不明白
Why must God die, I don't see.
物理學的兩大支柱是  量子論
The two great pillars of physics are: Quantum Theory,
針對所有微小粒子的理論
the laws that govern the very small particles,
電子什麼的  還有廣義相對論
electrons and so on, and General Relativity.
對  愛因斯坦
Ah, yes, Einstein.
愛因斯坦的理論  針對非常巨大的
Einstein's theory, the law that governs the very large,
恒星什麼的  但量子論  和相對論
planets and such, but Quantum, and Relativity...
別說  他們是不一樣的
Don't tell me... they're different?
一點也不一樣
They don't remotely play by the same rules.
如果宇宙裡只有土豆  那很簡單
If the world were all potatoes, then, easy
我們可以追溯回去  像斯蒂芬之前一樣
you could trace a precise beginning, as Stephen once did,
找到創世的那一刻
a moment of Creation.
哈利路亞  上帝是存在的
Hallelujah, God lives.
可是有了豌豆之後
If you incorporate peas into the menu,
就變得有點...
then it all goes a little...
...亂搞了
...tits up.
沒錯  瘋掉了
Yes, haywire.
-變成了沒有上帝的亂世  -天啊
- It all becomes a Godless mess. - Oh, dear.
愛因斯坦討厭豌豆
Einstein hated peas.
也就是量子論  他說
Quantum Theory, he said,
"上帝不擲骰子"
"God doesn't play dice with the universe."
可是他不僅玩骰子
Seems he not only plays the dice,
還扔到了我們看不到的地方
but he throws them where we can't find them.
上帝又變成了珍稀物種
God is back on the endangered species list.
他應該能適應的
Well, I expect He'll cope.
物理學又登場了
But physics is back in business.
對  物理學又登場了
Yes, physics is back in business.
我以前結過婚
I was married... actually.
可她突然去世了
But suddenly... she passed.
差不多一年了
Almost a year ago now.
白血病
It was leukemia.
她抗爭過  我也盡力照顧  可還是...
She fought it and I nursed her, but in the end...
我特別孤獨  獨守空房
I do get quite lonely... the tyranny of the empty room.
什麼的
And all that.
但音樂拯救了我  在唱詩班  教人彈琴
But... music is my salvation... teaching and playing.
算不上職業吧
Not really as a career,
反正我也沒有什麼野心
but I... I'm not that ambitious, so...
這算不算是罪  我也不知道
Is that a sin? I don't know.
問錯人了
Wrong man to ask.
-謝謝你們的招待  -謝謝你能來
- Thank you so much for having me. - Thank you for coming.
真是太...太好了
It was re... really... really wonderful.
如果有什麼能幫你的
If there's anything I can do to be of service... to you.
我是說幫你們家
To the family, I mean.
不要客氣
I would... consider it a privilege.
我沒有孩子  單身也沒什麼負擔
I have no children, or commitments.
我沒別的意思  就是想幫你  我...
I only mean that if I... could be of help, I've...
我肯定...  也算是
I'm... really, if I might find a purpose
幫我排解孤獨了
that would help alleviate my own situation.
-晚安  -晚安
- Good night. - Night.
我理解你的
I understand...
如果你需要幫助...
If you need help...
並且有人願意幫忙
If someone is prepared to offer...
我不會反對的
I won't object.
您是一人   也是萬物
Calls you one and calls you all,
他的領域  永存於世
to gain his everlasting hall.
生為救贖  解救眾生
Christ was born to save. Christ was born to save.
太棒了  大家可以走了
Great! Lovely! Okay! We can go!
-剛剛七點二十五  -謝謝
- Just going on seven twenty-five. - Thank you.
能...誰能給我留一份
I'm... could... could you all leave a copy of that?
我有話要跟你說
There's something I need to tell you.
什麼
What?
我懷孕了
I'm pregnant.
天啊  我...我還以為你和斯蒂芬
Gosh! I... I, um... I assumed that you and Stephen...
真...真是太棒了
Well, that's... that's really wonderful.
-確實  -真的  太美妙了
- It is. - Yes, it's wonderful.
-簡  恭喜你  -謝謝
- Congratulations, Jane. - Thank you.
說"茄子"  準備好了嗎
Everyone say "Cheese"! Ready?
我數到三  1  2  3
Count 3! 1, 2, 3...
茄子
Cheese!
-媽媽  -來了
- Mummy! - Just coming.
那個
Now, you know...
我一直都很支持你
I've always been supportive
不請人來幫忙
of your choice not to have home help,
但我們得想個長遠的辦法
but we need to find a permanent solution.
這種...這種...
This... this...
這種狀況不是長久之計
situation cannot continue,
你得趕緊找個常住的護工
you need to have a proper live-in nurse immediately.
有人照顧我
We have help.
你知道我什麼意思
Look... you know what I'm talking about.
我們雇不起護工
We can't afford a live-in nurse.
斯蒂芬  這樣不是辦法
Stephen, you need to find a way,
為了你的家人
for your family's sake...
你已經是世界名人了
you're world famous.
我是因為黑洞出名的  又不是搖滾樂
For black holes, not for rock concerts.
斯蒂芬  我沒開玩笑  這事不能拖
Stephen, this isn't funny, I believe it's urgent.
我們有權知道真相
We do have a right to know.
簡  我們有權知道
We have a right to know, Jane.
知道什麼
Know what?
蒂莫西的爸爸是誰...
Whose child Timothy is...
斯蒂芬還是喬納森
Stephen's, or Jonathan's?
我在你們眼裡就是那樣的人
That's what you think of me?
除了斯蒂芬
There is no way that Timothy
沒人可能是蒂莫西的爸爸
could have any other father than Stephen.
行了吧
Enough!
-喬納森  別走  -我該走了
- Jonathan, please don't go. - I have to go.
-所有人都說我們...  -那又怎樣
- Everybody's talking, and... - So, what does it matter?
我很難做下去  我只是想幫你們
It's difficult for me because I'm just trying to help.
我當然知道
I know you're trying to help
而且你幫了很大忙
and your help is valueless.
我想現在我最好還是
The best thing for me right thing right now,
還是...還是
I think, maybe if... if... if...
...退出你們的生活吧
...I just step back for now.
喬納森  別這樣
Please, Jonathan,
我們需要你  孩子需要你
we need you, the children need you,
我需要你  斯蒂芬也需要你
and I need you, and Stephen needs you.
-喬納森  -別說這些了
- Jonathan... - Don't think of it.
但是  簡  還有別的原因
But there's other things as well. Jane, I...
我對你有感覺
I have feelings for you.
我對你也是
And I have feelings for you, too.
簡  謝謝你
Thank you, Jane.
有人邀我去波爾多
I've been invited to Bordeaux.
-去哪  -波爾多
- Invited where? - To Bordeaux.
你要去波爾多
To Bordeaux?
馬克他們嗎
Mark and them?
學生們可以帶我去
Students can take me,
我知道你不喜歡坐飛機
I know you hate flying.
我確實討厭坐飛機
I do hate to fly.
你開車去吧  我們波爾多見
Bring the car, meet me in Bordeaux.
這樣孩子們也舒服些
Make the children comfy.
斯蒂芬  你一個人去太不方便了
It'd be too difficult to manage, Stephen.
讓喬納森陪你吧
Bring Jonathan.
他不一定願意去吧
I doubt he would be willing.
你好啊  斯蒂芬
Hello, Stephen.
-喝這個行嗎  -這個...
- Is this okay? - Well...
我是不會說出去的
I won't tell if you won't.
但是...
Just...
別喝多  你還得開車呢
bearing in mind you have to drive.
簡需要你的説明
Jane needs help.
薩拉  千萬記得
Sarah, you won't forget to give him
一著陸就給他注射藥物
the injection as soon as soon as you land, will you.
到賓館記得給我打個電話
And you'll call me when you get to the hotel.
-不會忘的  -保證
- I will. -Yes? Promise?
-一定不會  -好
- Yeah. - Good!
斯蒂芬
Stephen?
媽媽帶孩子去
Mum'll take the baby.
-她一會就到  -我們波爾多見
- She'll be here any minute. - See you in Bordeaux.
千萬注意
You be good.
-他們睡了嗎  -睡了
- They asleep? - Yeah.
喬納森
Jonathan.
Jonathan?
喬納森  斯蒂芬出事了
Jonathan, it's Stephen, he's been just taken ill,
他突然病重  被送到了醫院
he's in the hospital right now,
現在還在昏迷
he's in a coma.
他怎麼了
他感染了重度肺炎
現在全靠呼吸機維持
不知道他還能撐多久
我得問問我的同事
能不能撤掉呼吸機
你什麼意思
What are you talking about?
可以讓他沒有痛苦的離開
This way would be a painless end.
讓他脫離麻醉狀態
If we try to bring him round from the anesthetic
也不一定能保他的命
it's not sure he will survive resuscitation.
讓他脫離麻醉狀態
You have to bring him round from the anesthetic!
你確定真要這麼做
Are you sure it's what you want?
讓他呼吸的唯一方法
The only way of weaning him off the ventilator
就是實施氣管切開手術
would be to give him a tracheotomy,
在脖子上開刀  從喉嚨旁邊過去
a hole in the neck, by-passing the throat.
他就再也沒法說話了
He will never speak again.
沒得商量  必須要保住他的命
There's no question... Stephen must live.
需要什麼就用什麼
I will see he gets everything he needs.
然後轉院回劍橋
I will have him transferred back to Cambridge.
-他很可能下不了手術臺  -他能的
- He may not survive the journey. - Yes, he will.
我知道
I know.
我就...
I'll...
不去了
step back.
你東西都帶齊了嗎
Did you get everything in the car...
他的輪椅  設備什麼的
his chair, and his equipment, and everything?
再見了
Goodbye.
斯蒂芬
Stephen?
這是個拼字板
This is a spelling board.
我先說顏色
Firstly, you tell me
你要哪個顏色
what letter you want by blinking
就對我眨下眼睛
when I say the color of the group that contains that letter.
確定了顏色以後
Once I know the group,
我說到你要的字母
you can choose the character inside that group by
你就眨下眼睛
by blinking again when I say the color of each letter with that group...
...很簡單
...apparently
我們先試試吧
Let's just try.
綠色
Green.
藍色
Blue.
粉色
Pink.
黑色
Black.
紅色
Red.
斯蒂芬  用哪個顏色的字母
Blink to choose the color of
就對我眨下眼睛好嗎
the group of the letter that you want, Stephen.?
綠色
Green.
藍色
Blue.
粉色
Pink.
黑色
Black.
紅色
Red.
-稍等一下  -好的
- Just wait here. - Great.
她來了  很多人推薦她的
She's here, she comes highly recommended.
跟她和氣點
Promise not to eat her alive.
好嗎
Okay?
來啦
Here we are.
伊蓮  這是斯蒂芬
Elaine, Stephen.
斯蒂芬  這是伊蓮
Stephen, Elaine.
教授  很高興見到你
Lovely to meet you, Professor.
你一切都準備好了
Now, you should have everything you need.
還需要什麼再找我  我就在隔壁
But if there's anything else, I'll be right next door.
很好  我們可以馬上開始了
Great, I think we'll get straight to work.
簡  謝謝
Thank you, Jane.
-對了  拜託你關上門  -當然
- Oh, if you just close the doors. - Of course.
那我們就開始了
Let's get started then.
好了
Okay...
紅色
Red.
黃色
Yellow.
T
T.
綠色
Green.
黑色  E
Black... "E".
綠色  綠色  A
Green, green, "A".
茶
Tea.
你要一杯茶
You want a cup of tea?
好的
Okay.
要什麼口味
Any preference?
我知道你肯定都記住了
You've memorized the board, I know you have.
我沒用一天就記住了
I haven't got all day.
綠  綠  綠  黃
Green, green, green, yellow.
黃  B
Yellow, "B".
綠  藍  黑  粉  紅
Green, blue, black, pink, red.
紅色嗎
Red?
綠  黃  藍  藍
Green, yellow, blue, blue.
U 你要加糖和奶  是嗎
"U"... should be Builder's Tea, right?
他學的怎麼
Well, how did he get on?
他是我遇到過最聰明的人
You know, I think he's the most brilliant man I've ever met.
-你很幸運  -謝謝
- You're very lucky. - Thank you.
連他下面的土地都是偉大的...
You must worship the ground beneath...
他輪椅下麵
His wheels.
雖然生病了  他還是很幽默
And he's a perfect patient, he's so funny.
當你瞭解了他的時候...
When you read about him people...
先看他恢復得什麼樣
Let's see how he gets on,
好嗎  伊蓮
shall we, Elaine?
絕對好用
That's quite enough.
你看  它方便調節
As you can see, that it's quite adjustable,
可以變換角度  改變速度
and we can change the angle to whatever speed wants you there.
-這可是尖端科技  -要怎麼用
- Ya know, it's cutting-edge. - So, how does it work?
它有一個十分簡單的介面
It uses a very simple interface
你可以一個個字母的流覽
that scans through the alphabet
每次選一個字母
and selects each letter one at a time.
用了這個設備  教授大概
I mean, using this technique, the Professor can
每分鐘可以寫四個單詞
expect to write at about four words per minute.
很好啊  總比一分鐘一個要好
Good! Better than one a minute.
是啊  而且我從自動答錄機裡
Yes, and what I've done is taken the components
拿了些零件
from a telephone answering system, actually,
把文字轉換成語音
to convert the written text into synthesized speech.
聲音是有點像機器人  但總比...
I mean the voice sounds a little bit robotic, but...
我們來試試吧
Shall we give it a try?
-太棒了  -這是按鈕
- Great! - Here's the clicker.
右手嗎
Right hand?
開始吧
There ya go.
歡迎來到未來世界
Welcome to the future.
我叫斯蒂芬•霍金
My name is Stephen Hawking.
是美國口音的
It's American!
有問題嗎
Is that a problem?
這個...有別的選擇嗎
Oh, my goodness, well... is there another voice?
目前我只有這一種
It's the only one lately I have at the moment.
真棒
I think it's great.
取自歌曲《Daisy Bell》
黛西  黛西  告訴我你的答案  快點
Daisy, Daisy, give me your answer, do.
"說實話  親愛的  我不在乎"
"Frankly, my dear, I don't give a damn."
《神秘博士》中Dalek的經典臺詞
消滅
Exterminate!
我要寫本書
I will write a book.
關於什麼的
About what?
-時間  -時間
- Time. - Time.
時間的本質是什麼
What is the nature of time?
時間有沒有盡頭
Will it ever come to an end?
我們能不能回到過去
Can we go back in time?
也許未來  這些問題會變得
Some day these answers may seem
像地球繞著太陽轉一樣平常
as obvious to us as the Earth orbiting the sun,
抑或如烏龜塔般荒謬
or perhaps as ridiculous as a tower of tortoises.
古代人對宇宙的認識
唯有時間
Only time,
不管它是什麼  才能給我們答案
whatever that may be, will tell.
基普•索恩  致  斯蒂芬•霍金
劍橋大學
教授
Professor?
-是幫我朋友訂的  -當然...
- It is for a friend. - Of course it is...
男人都這麼說
That's what they all say.
教授  不用在我面前不好意思
You don't have to be embarrassed in front of me, Professor.
我瞭解你們男人
I know how men are like.
我們來看看吧
Shall we take a look?
來吧
There ya go.
對不起
Oh! I'm Sorry.
下一頁
Next one.
怎麼了
What?
《時間簡史》
我說過  我一直在努力尋找
So I said I had long been looking for
適用於整個宇宙的模型[模特]
a model of the universe.
我終於找到了她
I finally found her.
可不是嘛
I bet you did.
史蒂芬  打擾一下  合同來了
Stephen, I need to steal you, the contracts arrived.
簡  能再給我們一小會兒嗎
Could you just give us a minute, please, Jane?
好啦
There we go.
煥然一新
Like new.
我們是誰  為何存在於此
Who are we? Why are we here?
這兩個問題如果有答案
If ever learn this it would be
會是人類思想史上的重大突破
the ultimate triumph of the human reason,
因為那時  我們才真的理解了上帝
for then we would know the mind of God.
-你真這麼覺得  -是的
- Do you mean this? - Yes.
-當然  -所以你相信上帝存在了
- Of course. - So, you're acknowledging Him?
但是
However.
"但是"什麼
"However", what?
你不想讓我享受一下這一刻嗎
Are you actually going to let me have this moment?
不客氣
You're welcome.
我請伊蓮陪我去美國了
I have asked Elaine to travel with me to America.
她會照顧我的
She will look after me.
是嗎
Will she?
是的
Yes.
有人邀你去哪  你都會告訴我的
You always use to tell me when an invitation came in.
又得獎了  我也沒辦法
Another award, what can you do?
對不起
I'm sorry.
多少年了
How many years?
他們說只有兩年
They said two.
已經許多年了
You've had so many.
一切都會好起來的
Everything will be okay.
我愛過你
I have loved you.
我盡力了
I did my best.
小心點
Careful!
-那個留下  -好的
- No, that stays. - All right.
喬納森  再見
Goodbye, Jonathan.
謝謝
Thank you.
我1963年第一次見到霍金教授
I first met the Professor in 1963.
一轉眼  白駒過隙一樣
And there you are... time, where did it go?
看著他挑戰極限
It has been one of the great joys of my life
無論是科學上的
to watch this man
還是醫學上的  都使我倍感欣慰
defy every expectation, both scientific and personal.
有請我敬愛的同事
Please welcome onto the stage my esteemed colleague,
我親愛的朋友  霍金教授
my dear friend, Professor Hawking.
非常感謝  我們先來討論
Thank you! Could we please
第一個預選問題  好嗎  謝謝
have the first preselected question, thank you.
大家能聽到嗎
Can you hear me?
現在您已是名揚四海
Now you are recognized everywhere.
您是如何處理大家的關注的呢
How do you deal with all the attention?
最近  我在劍橋被一位遊客攔住
I was stopped recently by a tourist at Cambridge
他問我是否真的是霍金
who asked if I was the real Stephen Hawking.
我回答說我不是
I replied I was not,
霍金本人比我帥多了
and said the real one was much better looking.
1979年  您曾表示
In 1979, you talked about
有望在本世紀末
the possibility of a Theory of Everything.
發現適用萬物的理論
being discovered before the end of the century.
我現在預言我當時錯了
I now predict that I was wrong.
霍金教授  您說過您不信上帝
Professor Hawking, you have said you do not believe in God.
您說過您不信上帝
You have said you did not believe in God.
那麼您有什麼指導您的生活哲學嗎
Do you have a philosophy of life that helps you?
我們人類也不過是高級靈長類動物
It is clear that we are just an advanced breed of primates,
生活在一顆小星球上
on a minor planet orbiting
繞著一顆普通的恒星轉
around a very average star,
我們生活的銀河系之外
in the outer suburb of one
還有上億個星系
among a hundred billion galaxies...
然而  自人類文明誕生以來
But, ever since the dawn of civilization,
人們就沒有停止過
people have craved for
對世界根本規律的探索
an understanding of the underlying order of the world.
宇宙的邊界是什麼
There ought to be something
肯定有個特別的答案
very special about the boundary conditions of the universe.
但是還有比沒有邊界更特別的答案嗎
And what can be more special than that there is no boundary?
同樣  人類的潛力也不會有邊界
And there should be no boundary to human endeavor.
我們都是與眾不同的
We are all different.
無論生活多麼艱辛
However bad life may seem,
你總會有自己的方式發光
there is always something you can do, and succeed at.
生命不息  希望不止
While there is life, there is hope.
是斯蒂芬的來信
It's from Stephen.
天啊
Gosh.
你眼鏡總是這麼髒
Your glasses are always dirty.
霍金教授  霍金夫人  女王接見
Professor and Missus Hawking, Her Majesty the Queen.
恭喜你
Congratulations.
我的"榮譽伴侶"
My "Companion of Honor".
幹得好  主張自由社會主義的老頭子
Not bad for an old liberal socialist.
別擔心  你還是可以拒絕授銜的
Don't worry, you can decline the knighthood.
謝謝你請我來
Thank you for today.
真的很棒
It was extraordinary.
我們這一路一直都很棒  是吧
It's all been rather extraordinary, though, hasn't it?
你在寫什麼
What are you writing?
看看我們的成果
Look what we made.
《時間簡史》在全球銷量超過千萬
雖然已經72歲了  斯蒂芬依然沒有退休
繼續探索萬物理論
他婉拒了女王授予的騎士頭銜
簡拿到了西班牙詩歌的博士學位
她與喬納森喜結連理
簡和斯蒂芬依然是好朋友  現已經有三個孫輩
英國大學學位分等級
一般來說  一等學位要求均分70以上
霍金的本科三年只有一次考試  也就是畢業考試
由於緊張他發揮失常  成績處在一等與二等的邊緣
因此需要追加一次面試